\n"; } else { header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CSCI 903 Assignment 2

Overview

For this assignment, you are to complete the first assignment so the XHTML validation link actually works.

In addition, you are to “deploy” your web site by copying both files to your H:\htdocs directory in the lab. As discussed in class, you can access this directory while logged into any computer in the lab, and the effect will be to access the htdocs directory under your “home” directory on the Oak server.

Instructions

First, replace the <?xml…, <!DOCTYPE…, and <html… lines at the beginning of the web page with the following code:

<?php $html_attributes="lang='en'"; if ( array_key_exists("HTTP_ACCEPT", $_SERVER) && (stristr($_SERVER["HTTP_ACCEPT"], "application/xhtml") || stristr($_SERVER["HTTP_ACCEPT"], "application/xml") ) || (array_key_exists("HTTP_USER_AGENT", $_SERVER) && stristr($_SERVER["HTTP_USER_AGENT"], "W3C_Validator")) ) { $html_attributes = "xmlns='http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml' xml:lang='en'"; header("Content-type: application/xhtml+xml"); echo "<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>\n"; } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?> <!DOCTYPE html> <html <?php echo $html_attributes;?>>

Note: Be sure to paste this code at the very beginning of the web page. In particular, a blank line, or even a single space character, before the <?php line will “break” the web page (Why?), a very difficult bug to locate. (Why?).

Second, the file name for the web page has to be either index.php or index.xhtml. There are two reasons for this: (1) our Apache web servers are configured so that only files with a .php or .xhtml extension will be processed by the PHP module. If you don’t use one of those extensions (for example, if the extension is .html), Apache will pass the PHP code embedded in the file back to the browser, which will not know what to do with it, probably resulting in the user seeing an error message rather than your web page. (2) our Apache web servers are configured so that a request for a directory rather than a file will be treated as a request for a file named index.xhtml, index.php, or index.html located in that directory instead. This convention is one of the techniques we can use to simplify the URLs that users need to deal with.

The choice of whether to use the .php or .xhtml extension is up to you: as discussed in class, Dreamweaver will syntax-color either the HTML or the PHP code depending on which extension you use, but they are otherwise equivalent.

Create a subdirectory named css under your H:\htdocs directory, and put your stylesheet there. You will have to adjust the link to it in your index page to reflect this change.

These instructions assume you are already comfortable with accessing your account in the TREE lab. If not, TREE Lab Information can help. But note that some of the information there is out of date. Aside from the course numbers (this is CSCI 903, not 090.3), that information does not take into account the Apache web server that now runs on Oak, suggesting that you have to keep your work only in your Profile. Starting this semester, you will submit assignments by putting your code into your H:\htdocs directory.

Note that there is no requirement for you to use Dreamweaver for this assignment. You may do so if you wish, but you can use any code editor you like to prepare the two files for this assignment.

Test and Submit

Test

The most important part of coding is testing.
In this course, your assignments are to code web pages.
The most important part of your assignments is testing.
Look at the course syllabus and figure out how much of your course grade depends on testing your code.

You know from our discussion of “why XML” that the goal of this course is not only to introduce you to how to code, but how to code well. Starting with this assignment, there is a basic requirement for all assignments that you submit, whether mentioned explicitly in the assignment web page or not: test your code carefully before submitting it for grading. Make sure it does what it is supposed to do; make sure it handles “corner cases” correctly; and make sure it meets the specifications given in the assignment web page.

For this assignment, testing consists of putting your web page and style sheet in your H:\htdocs directory, and viewing it using the URL, http://oak.cs.qc.cuny.edu/~stpe9999. Of course, you have to substitute your own account for Perfect Student’s.

Make sure the page shows exactly what the assignment calls for: a level-1 heading, 15-20 paragraphs, and links to the XHTML and CSS validators at the bottom. Pay close attention to the beginning of the page to make sure there are no stray characters before the level-1 header, which would indicate a problem with the PHP code inserted at the beginning of the page.

Make sure the page behaves as it’s supposed to. Hover your mouse over everything, you are testing corner cases here, and be sure the text of each paragraph except the fourth one turns red when you hover over it, that the fourth one turns blue, and that hovering doesn't affect anything else on the page.

Make sure the two validation links work and that both give you no warnings or errors. The only exception is that the XHTML validator should give a warning that the “HTML5 Conformance Checker” (the validatory itself) is still experimental. Be sure the HTML validator recognizes the page as HTML5 and the CSS validator recognizes the page as CSS3.

Finally, make sure the web page is being delivered as XML. In class, we'll cover how to get the browser to show the request and reply headers so you can verify it; for now use your browser's "view source" option to look at the source code for your web page. The first line it shows has to be the <?xml… declaration. All major browsers have a view source option, but it’s in different menu places on different browsers. Look under the View menu for “Developer Tools” or “Page Source,” or ask Mr. G. for help. (If you don’t know who Mr. G. is, you can go to his website, where you will find answers to many questions.)

Correct anything that is wrong before submitting the assignment.

Submit

When you are ready to submit the assignment, send me an email:

Use CSCI 903 Assignment 2 as the Subject.
Put your account name in the message body.
You can include a message or questions in the email, but do not attach any files to it.

That’s it. When I get your email, I’ll look at your web page on oak, and send you back your grade by email. The grade for this assignment will simply be “ok” or “not ok”. See the course syllabus to learn how to interpret these grades.

To get full credit, you have to send the email to me by midnight of the due date (February 12).

As soon as you receive the email from me with your grade, use the form on the course schedule to be sure I have recorded your grade correctly

Class Schedule — XHTML — CSS

\n"; } else { header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CSCI 903 Assignment 3

Overview

This is a multipart assignment in which your course web site’s home index page is to provide a summary of projects done to date. Once this index page has been set up, the site is to adjust automatically to show new projects, when projects were last modified, and summary information about each project.

New Account For Course

With this project, we are also changing the “remote” server for your site from oak to babbage: I was unable to get the user-specific document root directories on oak to work as I had hoped I could. Your H: dive will continue to be available as your home directory when you access your lab account, and you should continue to use your lab account to write your code for the assignments. You can continue to work from off-campus using RDC, and in that way you can continue to use Dreamweaver in the lab. But, as explained in the TREE Lab Information page, and the pages linked from it, you are not required to use the TREE Lab if you have a different development environment you are already comfortable with.

But now you have another, separate, account with the same user name and password as your TREE Lab account. This one is on babbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu. The account is set up with a directory named htdocs in your home directory, just like (but separate from) the htdocs directory on your H: drive in the lab. The URL is the same as the one you used on oak: a tilde (~) followed by your account name.

To copy your files to your htdocs directory from another computer, using Dreamweaver’s sites feature, Aptana Studio, WinSCP, Fugu, or some other program, you need to know the pathname to your home directory. For Perfect Student with a student id of 99999999, it's:

/Volumes/Sensitive/Library/WebServer/Documents/babbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu/cs903/stpe9999/htdocs

Substitute your own account name for stpe9999.

Before you start work on this assignment, you need to make sure you can copy the code you develop in the lab or off campus to your babbage account, and to access it using a URL like http://babbage.cs.qc.cuny.edu/~stpe9999 .

Instructions

For this step, you are to set up your htdocs directory so that there are three subdirectories, one for each of the first three assignments. Perfect Student used “Assignment_01,” “Assignment_02,” and “Assignment_03” for the three directory names, but you can use more descriptive names if you like. Just be sure there are no spaces in the directory names because they will be used in URLs, where spaces sometimes require extra effort to get them to work right.

The only thing that goes in the Assignment 3 subdirectory (for now) is the stylesheet for assignment 3. The index page for this assignment is to be the index page for the htdocs directory. Create that index page using the PHP and <footer> element with validation links like the code in the previous assignments to start.

Make the title and h1 elements of the index page tell what the web site is about. Perfect Student used the title, “Perfect Student’s Assignments for CSCI 903,” but you can make yours anything you like. If you use an apostrophe in your h1 element as Perfect Student did, it must be typographically correct (a right single “curly” quote(’), not a prime symbol (').

Test your web site to make sure your new index page displays properly and that both validation links give no errors and no warnings except for the one about HTML5 from the XHTML validator.

Now add a PHP block between the h1 and footer elements. This block is to display an h2 element for each file or directory in your htdocs directory, with the name of the file or directory as the contents of the heading.

Use the PHP opendir() function to get a PHP “resource” that represents the current directory. See the PHP Manual for more information on this function.
Use a while loop to get the names of the files and directories by calling readdir() repeatedly. Echo the names of the directories inside h2 elements; ignore the files. The first Example on the opendir() page of the PHP Manual shows how to do this, except you have to put the file or directory name inside an h2 element and you are not to display the file type. (It will always be “dir.” Lookup the is_dir() function in the PHP Manual if you are not sure what it does.

Use a stylesheet to make your web page look “good.”

Test your code! Try adding and removing subdirectories to your htdocs directory to make sure it displays them correctly. Be sure both validators continue to give your site a clean bill of health.

Send me an email with “CSCI 903 Assignment 3A” as the subject, and be sure to include you account name in the message body. The assignment is due by midnight of the due date (March 5).

Do not include this step in your web site until you have received your grade for the previous step of the project.

There are some directories in your htdocs directory that have nothing to do with your assignments. If you use Dreamweaver, it will place a _notes there; if you use Git, it will place a .git directory there; all directories have two extra directory entries: ., which always represents the current directory, and .., which always represents the directory above the current directory. In Unix-based systems (Linux; Apple OS X), file and directory names that begin with a dot are hidden from normal directory listings, and you should eliminate them from your list of h2 elements. That is, you need to examine the first character of each directory name to see if it is a dot or an underscore (to handle Dreamweaver’s _notes directories).

To do this filtering, you will have to start working with directory names using PHP’s string manipulation features. You will also need to learn how to manage the while loop so it skips the unwanted directories. Both of these topics will be covered in class.

For this step you are also to turn your h2 text into clickable links to the appropriate assignment directories.

Finally, look inside each directory to see if there is a file named README, README.md, or README.txt there. If so, pass the contents of the file to the Markdown() function and display the results in a div element right after the h2 element. If none of those files is there, display a paragrah saying there is no project description available. Do not put such a file in the directory for the first assignment, put one named README in the second assignment directory, and put one named README.md in the third assignment directory so you can test that this requirement works correctly. (What’s not being tested?)

Test your code carefully, and send me email with CSCI 903 Assignment 3B as the subject, and your account name in the message body. The due date is midnight March 12.

Do not include this step until you have received your grade for the previous step.

For the last step in this project, you are to add the name and latest date at which any file in that directory or any of its subdirectories was modified. Also, add an empty index.php file to the directory for Assignment 3 so user will not be able to browse the directory from the web.

Test the entire project carefully, and send me an email with CSCI 903 Assignment 3C as the subject and your account name in the message body. The due date is midnight March 19.

Class Schedule — XHTML — CSS

\n"; } else { header("Content-type: $mime_type; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CSCI 903 Assignment 4

Overview

This is a multipart assignment in which you will develop a secure login mechanism for your web site.

Instructions

Set up the project directory.

Create a new directory for this assignment. Perfect Student called it “Assignment_04,” but you may use a more descriptive name, like “Login,” if you like. Create a subdirectory named css for the stylesheet(s) for the project, and create an index page that will contain the login form for the project.

You will need to decide whether the PHP code for processing the form data will be in a separate file or embedded in the index page. Either approach is all right, and you do not have to make that decision just yet.

Put a form element on the page

that submits its form data to a separate page called display_form_data.php in the project directory. Use the POST method. Include a text input element for the user’s name and a password input element for the user’s password. Include a fieldset with legend, labels for the two inputs, and a submit button that says “Login.” Use the tabindex attribute on the input and button elements so that the tab key takes users first to the password, then to the username, and then to the submit button.

This is an academic exercise: the tab sequence is strange, and there are questions about using legends and fieldsets, which can be mimicked using CSS. The idea is to give you some experience with these features so you can decide what role they will (or will not) play in your later career.

Create the display_form_data.php page.

Set it up as a regular XHTML5 page like all the others in this course. If the array of form data is available, display a suitable page title and a table containing all the form data submitted, using the foreach loop given in class on April 16 to generate the table rows. If the $_POST array is not available, display a page title saying there is no form data instead.

Add a file named README.md to the project directory.

Enter a description of the project there so that it shows up when the user visits your site’s home page.

Use a stylesheet to make your index page look “good.”

Put it in the css subdirectory for the assignment.

Test your code

with different patterns of input, including empty values. Try accessing the page without submitting a form.

Be sure both validators continue to give your site a clean bill of health.

Send me an email

with “CSCI 903 Assignment 4A” as the subject, and be sure to include you account name in the message body. The assignment is due by midnight of the due date (April 18).

“Sanitize” all form data.

Write a function named sanitize() that will prevent SQL injection attacks by converting apostrophe characters (') to “curly” quotes (‘ or ’), by converting double dashes (--) into em dashes (—), and converting semicolons (;) into a numeric HTML character entities (&#x3B; or &#59;). You can use str_replace() to handle double dashes and semicolons, but you will need to use preg_replace() to handle the quote characters, as shown in class.

For example, the first statement below replaces all double quote characters that are at the beginning of a string (^) or preceded by whitespace (\s) with left curly quotes. The parentheses around ^|\s captures that part of the matched string so that it can be re=inserted before the “ by using $1 in the replacement string. The second statement simply replaces any remaining double quotes with right curly quotes. Just change the double quotes to single quotes for this part of the assignment.

$returnVal = preg_replace('/(^|\s)"/', '$1“', $returnVal); $returnVal = str_replace('"', '”', $returnVal);

To paraphrase an old joke:

“6 munce ago I kudnt even spel reglur xpreshin and now i я one”

Prevent cross-site scripting attacks by converting all ampersand (&), less-than (<), and greater-than (>) characters to XML character entities (&amp;, &lt;, and &gt;, respectively).

While you’re at it, convert double apostrophes (") to curly quotes as well (“ or ”).

Use your sanitize() function to convert all form data into “safe” strings which, except for the conversion to curly quotes and substitution of em dashes for double dashes, look just like what the user typed into the form.

Test your form thoroughly

and carefully. Don’t forget Little Bobby Tables!

Be sure both validators continue to give your site a clean bill of health.

Send me an email

with “CSCI 903 Assignment 4B” as the subject, and be sure to include you account name in the message body. The assignment is due by midnight of the due date (April 25).

Do not add this step to your web site until you have received your grade for the previous step of the project.

Encode passwords using crypt()

using the SHA-512 algorithm with the date and time of the encryption (YYYY-MM-DD HH:MM) as the salt. Verify that the encrypted password is being computed by displaying it in place of the plain password in your display_form_data.php page. You can’t completely test this code for correctness until you set up a database to save user names and passwords.

Test your code.

The password field should show a string that starts with '$6$2013-05-01 13:57$...' but with the actual date and time in the sixteen characters following the second dollar sign, and the encrypted password in place of the '...' following the third dollar sign. Only in the following step will you be able to test whether the encrypted password “works” or not.

Be sure both validators continue to give your site a clean bill of health.

Send me an email

with “CSCI 903 Assignment 4C” as the subject, and be sure to include you account name in the message body. The assignment is due by midnight of the due date (May 2).

Do not add this step to your web site until you have received your grade for the previous step of the project.

Set up your database and use it to save user names and passwords

. Look at the documentation for SQLite3 at http://www.sqlite.org/ and the documentation for the PHP SQLite3 interface in the PHP Manual.

I have written a mini-tutorial on using SQLite3 with PHP to help you get started.

I have set up an empty SQLite3 database that your code can read and write in your home directory: it’s called cs903.db. Since your project directory is two levels below your home directory, use ../../cs903.db to open it.

Modify display_form_data.php

to check whether the user is in the database or not. If not, insert the username and encrypted password, and display a message saying the user was successfully registered before displaying the table with the form data.

If the user is already in the database, check that the password the user supplied is correct. If it is, display a message greeting the user by name before displaying the table with the form data. If not, display a statement saying that the login failed before displaying the form data.

Send me an email

with “CSCI 903 Assignment 4D” as the subject, and be sure to include you account name in the message body. The assignment is due by midnight of the due date (May 7).

Do not add this step to your web site until you have received your grade for the previous step of the project.

This is a somewhat open-ended part of the assignment, with a required portion plus some ideas for extra features you may add to your project for extra credit—if you have time.

Use session variables to manage error conditions (Required).

If the user does not log in correctly (missing username or missing/wrong password), redirect them to the index page for the assignment, and display an error message above the login form there.

If you have not done so already, this step will require you to put the code for checking the form data at the top of the display form data page, before the HTTP headers get sent, because the headers() function cannot be called once any part of the response message has been output. [Actually, PHP provides a mechanism called “output buffering” that could be used, but it’s not worth the trouble in this case.]

Code to save an error message in a session variable and redirect the user to the index page:

$_SESSION['error_msg'] = "This is a meaningful error message"; header('Location: index.php'); exit;

As discussed in class, you will have to call the session_start() function at the start of both the index page and the display form data page in order to establish communication between them.

And you will need to modify the index page to display the error message if there is one. Once an error message has been displayed, it should be deleted: unset($_SESSION['error_msg']), for example.

Require new users to enter the initial password twice (Required).

This step is required, but the next one is optional. Nonetheless, you should set this step up in anticipation of the optional step.

Instead of just one password field, provide three: one for the current password (to be used by current users), and two for a new password and a repeated new password. New users have to enter the same password in both the new and repeat-new boxes in order to register successfully. Existing users have to enter their current password correctly in order to log in successfully.

Allow users to change their password (Optional).

Registered users enter their current password and a new password (repeated) to change their password. This will require use of an UPDATE SQL statement with a WHERE clause to limit the update to just the one user.

Provide a “manage profile” page (Optional).

Add columns to your users table for additional information, such as email addresses, real name, home address, phone number, favorite color, whether to receive spam, etc.

Provide a form on the display form data page that users can use to manage their profile information.

Provide a “manage users” page (Optional).

Create a list of privileged users (administrators). This can be as simple as an extra boolean column in the users table. Be sure user “vickery” with password “secret” is included in this list.

Provide administrators with a table showing all the users and the information about them. Allow administrators to delete users and/or to edit any user’s profile.

Send me an email

with “CSCI 903 Assignment 4E” as the subject, and be sure to include you account name in the message body. The assignment is due by midnight of the due date (May 21).

To receive credit for any optional parts of the assignment that you complete, you must include a message in your email telling me what to look for.

Note: May 21 is the absolute cutoff date for all assignments in this course. Absolutely no credit will be given for work submitted after that date.

Class Schedule — XHTML — CSS